A Guide to the Angelica Schuyler Church Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Angelica Schuyler Church 1716-1865
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11245, 11245-a
84 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession #11245 was purchased by the Library on June 26, 1996 from Ken Lopez, Bookseller. Accession #11245-a was purchased by the Library on July 20, 2005 from Mida van Zuylen Dunn.
Biographical Notes
Following are notes on the family taken from A God-Child of Washington: A Picture of the Past by Katharine Schuyler Baxter.
Philip John Schuyler married Catharine van Rensselaer and had issue: John Bradstreet Schuyler, Philip Schuyler, Angelica Schuyler, Margaret ("Peggy") Schuyler, Elizabeth ("Betsy") Schuyler, Cornelia Schuyler, and, Catharine v[an] R[ensselaer] Schuyler. John Bradstreet Schuyler married Elizabeth van Rensselaer in 1787 and had issue: Philip Schuyler. Angelica Schuyler married John Barker Church and had issue: Philip hurchand Catharine ("Kitty") Church. Margaret Schuyler(-1801) married Stephen van Rensselaer ca. 1784 and had issue: Catherine Schuyler van Rensselaer(died age 12) and Stephen van Rensselaer; van Rennsselaer married Cornelia Patersonin 1802. Elizabeth Schuyler married Alexander Hamiltonon December 14, 1780. Cornelia Schuyler married Washington Morton.
Stephen van Rensselaer(1742-1824) married Catherine Livingston, daughter of Philip Livingston and Christiana Ten Broeckand had issue: Stephen van Rensselaer, Philip van Rensselaer, and Elizabeth van Rensselaer. Stephen van Rensselaer(1764-1839) married Margaret Schuyler ca. 1784. Philip van Rensselaer(1766-1824) married Anne de Peyster Cortlandt in 1787. Elizabeth van Rennsselaer(1768-) married John Bradstreet Schuyler in 1787; she married secondly, John Bleecker, in 1800. Catherine Livingston van Rensselaer, after the death of Stephen van Rensselaer, married Domini Eilardus Westerlo and had issue: Rensselaer Westerlo and Catherine Westerlo. Rensselaer Westerlo married Jane Lansing. Catherine Westerlo married John Woodworth.
Robert Livingston(1654-) married Miss [ ] Schuyler and had issue: Philip Livingston, Gilbert Livingston, and Robert Livingston. Philip Livingston had a son Philip Livingston, who was born in Albany, 1716, and died in York, Pennsylvania, 1778; he was a signer of the Declaration of Independence.
Scope and Content
There are 84 items, 1716-1865, chiefly letters of Angelica Schuyler Church(1756-1815) and other family members, including her husband John Barker Church, brother-in-law Alexander Hamilton(1757-1804), father Philip John Schuyler, and brother-in-law Stephen van Rensselaer(1764-1839). Other notable correspondents include: Justus Erich Bollman(1769-1821); Charles James Fox(1749-1806); Thomas Jefferson(1743-1826); Marquis de Lafayette(1757-1834); Abraham Lincoln(1809-1865); Winfield Scott(1786-1866); Baron von Steuben(1730-1794); Charles Maurice de Talleyrand-Perigord(1754-1838); and, George Washington(1732-1799).
Topics of interest include national politics and foreign affairs including the politics of Alexander Hamiltonand Thomas Jefferson, the French Revolution, Marquis de Lafayetteand his imprisonment, and the War of 1812; travel in Polandand Austriaand in England; trade in Americaand India; and, family and personal matters. Persons mentioned or discussed include Marquis de Lafayetteand his family, Marquis de La Tour(1770-1853); Philip John Schuyler; John Trumbull(1756-1843), Maria Cosway, Mary Jefferson Eppes[Mrs. John Wayles Eppes] (1778-1804), Martha Jefferson Randolph[Mrs. Thomas Mann Randolph] (1772-1808), and Madam de Corny.
Angelica Schuyler Churchwas the daughter of General Philip John Schuyler, a Major General in the Continental Army and a member of the Continental Congress. He later served as one of the first two United StatesSenators from New York. Angelica Schuylermarried John Barker Church, a British businessman, who was George Washington's Commissary General during the Revolution and later became a member of the English Parliament. Church had fled Englandafter a duel and later, using the name John Carter, eloped with Angelica Schuylerand became a successful entrepreneur. Mrs. Church traveled in social circles which included the most prominent figures of her time. In Paris, she was introduced to Thomas Jeffersonby her close friend Maria Cosway; Church's daughter Catharine ("Kitty") Churchwas a playmate of Jefferson's daughter, Mary ("Polly") Jefferson. These social connections made her instrumental in the release of Lafayette from the prison at Olmutz, Austria. Mrs. Church's sister, Elizabeth Schuyler, married Alexander Hamilton.
The Church archive contains correspondence from the period of the founding of America, including letters from two of the Founding Fathers, Alexander Hamiltonand Thomas Jefferson, whose personal and political differences helped shape the course of political dialogue in the early days of the country. The letters are rich in personal and historical detail. Both Hamilton and Jefferson write to Mrs. Church with a combination of intimacy and respect. These letters complement the recorded history of the private lives of two of the most prominent statesment in the early years of independence, and provides evidence of their practical concerns. There are other letters from Jefferson to Church held in the Library of Congress.
Following the biographical notes is an annotated listing of each letter and document. The majority of the correspondence has been described; letters written in French or other foreign language have not been described.
A digital exhibition drawn from these papers is available online.
Contents List
- Papers
  - Francois Barthelmey to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1795 September 3; ALS, 2 p.
    In French. Mentions [John Barker] Church, has sent her letter to James Monroe, thanks her for news of the Blair family, tells of friends who fell under the reign of Robespierre, remarks on the death of Andre Chenier, noting that his brother [Marie Joseph] Chenier is in the Convention.
  - Justus Erich Bollman, Breslau, Poland, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1794 July 9; ALS, 4 p.
    Relates description and history of areas in Poland, including Silesia, Waldenburg, Silberberg, Glatz, Spielberg, Landek, and Wel[fors]ground; recites tale of Henriette Lucie Dillon, Marquis de La Tour, and Marie Joseph Paul, Marquis de Lafayette; and, writes about his own experiences in these and other locations.
  - Justus Erich Bollman, Vienna, Austria, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1794 July 30; ALS, 4 p.
    Relates description and history of areas in Poland and Austria, including Breslau, Tarnow[itz], Troppan, Brunn, Spielberg, and Olmutz; recites tales of Marquis de Lafayette, Marquis de La Tour, and Mr. Bournonville and other french prisoners; mentions Prince Colloredo (Hieronymus, Count von Colloredo--Mansfeld) (1775-1822), Bishop of Kunitz, Count Lamberg, and Botta, Governor of Moravia, Czechoslovakia; and, writes about his own experiences in these and other locations.
  - Angelica Schuyler Church, New York, to the Prince of Wales., 1811 March 25; ALS, 3 p.
    Expresses gratitude and affection for the Prince's reception of her son and hopes that her eldest son Philip will have the honor to present this letter.
  - John Barker Church, London, England, to Catharine Church Cruger, New York, New York., 1817 July 24; ALS, 3 p.
    Relates that the disturbances have been exaggerated by the administration for the purpose of the reform of Parliament and that the French government appears to gather strength; gives news of Richard [ ] and his travels to Paris.
  - Princess de Craon to "Kitty" Cruger, New York, New York., 1830 November 1; ALS, 3 p.
    Relates events in July Revolution of 1830. Plans to return to Paris. Currently being watched by the National Guard.
  - Princess de Craon to "Kitty" Cruger., 1830 August 11; ALS, 4 p.
    Mentions the July Revolution of 1830 and the cannon fire she heard. Criticizes Lafayette stating that "All reasonable persons damn this old man." Comments on Charles X.
  - Princess de Craon to "Kitty" Cruger., 1830 September 6; ALS, 4 p.
    Mentions the July Revolution of 1830 and what is happening in Paris
  - Princess de Craon, Paris, France, to ["Kitty" Cruger., 1830 November 15; ALS, 4 p.
    Discusses the July Revolution of 1830, and the fortunes of family and friends. Notes that the "court of Louis-Philippe is very thrifty."
  - Princess de Craon, Paris, France, to ["Kitty" Cruger., 1831 January 25; ALS, 4 p.
    Notes that Lafayette is in retirement and sends news of friends and people ruined by the "Glorious Days."
  - Princess de Craon to ["Kitty" Cruger., 1831 March 12; ALS, 4 p.
    A sympathy letter; also discusses riots, school closings, the destruction of an archbishop's library by a mob, and the plight of pensioners and old friends.
  - John Cruger, New York, New York, to Philip Livingston, Albany, New York., 1716 October 15; ALS, 1 p.
    In Dutch.
  - D'Ageno, Pall Mall, London, England, to Angelica Schuyler Church, Windsor, England., [1785] November 26; ALS, 1 p.
    Social amenities.
  - D'Ageno, London, England, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1786 October 27; ALS, 4 p.
    Discusses impending plans while visiting the Churches, including visits to the observatory and Windsor Castle, and an introduction to an Italian party of Prince Rezzonico, Count Soderini, and Count Luchesi. News of the Cosways and a visit with Maria Cosway's sister Charlotte.
  - D'Ageno, London, England, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1787 August 2; ALS, 4 p.
    Discusses news of the Cosways, de Cornys, and Wynns and plans while visiting "Down-place."
  - D'Ageno, "Armida Garden at Cosway," to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1787 September 21; ALS, 4 p.
    Mentions news of the Cosways, Maria Cosway's sister Charlotte, and Lady Littleton. Discusses the beauty of Maria Cosway and Angelica Church; gives advice and expressing confidence that "prudence will rule your future conduct" concerning the apparent misunderstanding between Maria Cosway and herself.
  - Charles James Fox (1749-1806), Bath, England, to [ ]., LS, 1 p.
    Concerns the correspondent's inattention to the recipient's commands respecting Mr. Schuyler.
  - Alexander Hamilton to [Angelica Schuyler Church]., 1785 August 3; ALS, 3 p.
    Beseeches her not to make her permanent home away from America, and expresses affection and friendship for her and [John Barker] Church. #11245-a
  - Alexander Hamilton, New York, New York, to Angelica Schuyler Church, London, England., 1789 January 7; LS, 1 p.
    Mentions his plans for tomorrow to "open the budget" as Secretary of the Treasury, and wishes for their safe arrival in England.
  - Alexander Hamilton, New York, New York, to Angelica Schuyler Church, with note from E[lizabeth Schuyler] Hamilton., 1789 November 8; ALS, 2 p.
    Heartfelt feelings of affection and friendship and loss in the absence of both John and Angelica Church following the sailing of their vessel to England.
  - Alexander Hamilton, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1791 January 31; ALS, 1 p.
    Mentions politics, the offer of an office to her father, Philip John Schuyler, and his progress on the Finances of America as Secretary of the Treasury.
  - Elizabeth Schuyler Hamilton to Angelica Schuyler Church, with three-page letter from Alexander Hamilton., 1791 October 2; ALS, 2 p.
    Relays compliments from George Washington who lives on Market Street in Robert Morris' house; mentions "Peggy" [Margaret Schuyler] and [Stephen] van Rensselaer. Mr. Hamilton writes of his affection for Angelica and comments on her intimacy with princes.
  - Alexander Hamilton (1757-1804) to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1791 November; ALS, 2 p.
    References to national affairs. Treasury conflicts.
  - Alexander Hamilton to Angelica Schuyler Church., [1793 February.; ALS, 1 p.
    References to international and national affairs. At that time the support by the Jeffersonian Antifederalist for the French Revolutionary cause was lessened; Hamilton comments, "On a certain subject we agree...And though I am in a minority here...It is gaining strength---Your countrymen are zealous but they are not mad." During that time there had also been an official inquiry into the condition of the Treasury, and an subsequent call on February 28 censuring Hamilton did not pass; Hamilton comments, "Our own Jacobins have made a violent effort against me, but a complete victory has been gained to their utter confusion."
  - Alexander Hamilton, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1793 December 27; ALS, 2 p.
    References to national and international affairs. Mentions a political campaign and [probably] treasury conflicts. During this time American neutrality in the war between England and France had been threatened; Hamilton comments, "... or the certainty of a war between this country and some European Power--"
  - Alexander Hamilton to Angelica Schuyler Church, Broadway, New York., [1794] January 22; ALS, 2 p.
    Mentions a social visit with Philip John Schuyler and his wife [Catharine van Rensselaer Schuyler] and "a lady for whom I have a particular friendship"; John Trumbull, the artist; and, Stephen van Rensselaer and his wife Margaret Schuyler van Rensselaer.
  - Alexander Hamilton, Bedford, Pennsylvania, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1794 October 23; ALS, 1 p.
    References to national affairs, most likely the Whiskey Rebellion. Hamilton comments, "I am thus far...on my way to attack and subdue the wicked insurgents of the West---" and further explains his involvement, "Twas very important there should be no mistake in the management of the affair--and I might contribute to prevent one." Sends news of the insurrection to [John] Jay (1745-1829) and [William] Pinkney (1764-1822) through Mrs. Church.
  - Alexander Hamilton to Angelica Schuyler Church, London, England., 1796 September 24; ALS, 2 p.
    Expresses regret that John Barker and Angelica Church have delayed their plans to visit. Mentions a Mrs. Grattan.
  - Alexander Hamilton, New York, New York, to [Philip John] Schuyler., 1801 March 22; ALS, 2 p.
    Discusses the fire onboard the vessel which was docked in Havenshaw Bay.
  - Thomas Jefferson, Paris, France, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1788 February 17; ALS (copy), 2 p.
    Mentions Madam de Corny, "Kitty" [Catharine Church] and the girls and invites Mrs. Church to Monticello. Compares the beauty and charm of America to Europe. Affectionate and complimentary.
  - Thomas Jefferson to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1788 August 17; ALS (copy), 2 p.
    Gratitude for the gift of the urn. Mentions the John Trumbull portrait of himself and his own friendship with [Maria] Cosway and Angelica Church. Refers to his plans to carry animals and plants back to America in the spring and request that she meet him and his daughters in Havre, France. Mentions serving in Congress in 1775 with Philip John Schuyler. Relates that he left "Kitty" [Catharine Church] at the Chaussee d'Antin and consulted with Madam de Corny of the Convent.
  - Thomas Jefferson, Paris, France, to Angelica Schuyler Church, London, England., 1788 September 21; ALS (copy), 2 p.
    Discusses plans to execute her commission for the volumes of the Antiquites d' Herculaneum. Mentions "Kitty" [Catharine Church] and her writing in French and Madam de Corny and a mishap in her carriage. Refers to the question of the new Constitution and comments that "the tender breasts of ladies were not formed for political convulsion..."
  - Thomas Jefferson, New York, New York, to Angelica Schuyler Church, London, England., 1790 June 23; ALS (copy), 2 p.
    Comments that he wishes "Mr. Church could think our Congress as agreeable a field of service as that he has chosen..." and that he is not without friends in America. Mentions "Kitty" [Catharine Church], "Polly" [Mary Jefferson] living with an aunt, [John] Trumbull and his paintings, and Madam de Corny.
  - Thomas Jefferson, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1793 June 7; ALS (copy), 1 p.
    Mentions Monsieur de Noailles (a kinsman of Madam Lafayette). Inquires of Madam de Corny and [Maria] Cosway. Comments that he thinks America is "the only country of tranquility, and should be the asylum of all those who wish to avoid the scenes which have crushed our friends in Paris."
  - Thomas Jefferson, Germantown, Pennsylvania, to Angelica Schuyler Church, London, England., 1793 November 27; ALS (copy), 2 p.
    Comments on her letter of August 19th, with the extract from Lafayette, and that "the influence of the United States has been put into action" to effect the release of Lafayette. Comments on the news of Madam de Corny being a victim of the times and of [Maria] Cosway being in a convent. Remarks that at the beginning of the new year, "I am to be liberated from the hated occupations of politics, & to sink into the bosom of my family, my farm & my books."
  - Thomas Jefferson, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to John Church., 1793 December 11; ALS (copy), 1 p.
    Replies to his letter of August 16th to President [George Washington] concerning the misfortunes of Lafayette, and assures him that the means most likely to effect his release have been employed.
  - Thomas Jefferson, "Monticello," Albemarle County, Virginia, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1795 September 8; LS (copy), 1 p.
    Writes about being home with his family and wishes that she and her husband were nearby. Wishes to hear news of Catharine [Church]. Mentions that his daughter [Martha Jefferson] Randolph is absent and writing a letter to [Maria] Cosway.
  - Thomas Jefferson, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1797 May 24; ALS (copy), 2 p.
    Welcomes her home to her native country and comments that the agitations of Europe have reached even the United States. Inquires of Madam de Corny, [Maria] Cosway, and Catharine [Church].
  - Thomas Jefferson, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1798 January 11; ALS (copy), 1 p.
    Mentions Mrs. [James] Monroe, Madam de Corny's improved situation, and receiving a letter from Catharine [Church]. Comments on news from a Mr. Niemcewitz, a Polish gentleman, that [Maria] Cosway has thrown herself into religion since the loss of her daughter and other circumstances.
  - Thomas Jefferson, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania to Catharine Church., 1798 January 11; ALS (copy), 1 p.
    Affectionate letter. News of his daughters, "Maria" [Mary Jefferson] Eppes and [Martha Jefferson] Randolph. Invites her to Monticello.
  - Thomas Jefferson, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Catharine Church, New York, New York., 1800 January 22; ALS (copy), 1 p.
    Writes fond remembrances of her visits, and mentions his daughters [Martha Jefferson] Randolph and [Mary Jefferson] Eppes and that the latter has become a mother.
  - Thomas Jefferson, Washington, to Catharine Church, New York, New York., 1801 March 27; ALS (copy), 1 p.
    Comments on being elected to the presidency of the United States: "The post is not enviable, as it affords little exercise for social affections. There is something within us which makes us wish to have things conducted in our own way, and which we generally fancy to be patriotism. This passion is gratified by such a position." Mentions that Maria [Mary Jefferson Eppes] and [Martha Jefferson] Randolph being with child.
  - Thomas Jefferson, Washington, to Catharine Church Cruger., 1808 December 15; ALS (copy), 1 p.
    Regrets not being able to assist in giving the license solicited by [J. C.] Cruger. Comments on [Martha Jefferson] Randolph and her large family.
  - Thomas Jefferson Portrait, n.d.; Printed
    Etching. Inset of Jefferson showing the draft of Declaration of Independence to Franklin and Adams.
  - Marquis de Lafayette, Vianen, [Netherlands], to Angelica Schuyler Church, New York, New York., 1799 April 19; ALS, 2 p.
    Relates his feelings toward her, writing that he is "bound by such sentiments of affection and gratitude." Reveals the present situation of his family, mentioning his wife's illness; his daughter Anastasia and her husband Charles Latour Maubourg giving him two granddaughters, one of whom they lost; and, possibly being able to embark for America with George [his son George Washington de Lafayette]. Refers to his own political and personal concerns, particularly in reference to his [former] fellow prisoner Bureau Puzy who is planning to settle his family in America; praises his character and accomplishments; and, recommends him highly to the Churches. Mentions having heard of the appointment of three plenipotentiary ministers to France; his intelligence from Paris gives him good reason to think the French government wishes for a reconciliation.
  - Marquis de Lafayette, [Autenol...Noreal, France] to Angelica Schuyler Church, New York, New York., 1805 May 14; ALS, 2 p.
    Expresses his lament at the distance between them and his affection and respect for his friend. Discusses the consultation between the American minister and himself to determine whether or not he should follow Mr. [ ] Livingston over to New York and possibly risk captivity. Mentions Madam de Corny.
  - Marquis de Lally-Tollendal, Dimanche, to [Angelica Schuyler Church]., 1794 May; LS, 3 p.
    Writes concerning the fate of friends, emigres and Lafayette during the reign of terror. Discusses his book.
  - M. de Liancoeur to Angelica Schuyler Church, London, England., LS, 1 p.
    Solicits letters of recommendation.
  - Abraham Lincoln, Executive Mansion, Washington, to [ ]., 1862 August 18; ALS, 1 p.
    Introduction for Louis McLane Hamilton, descendant of Alexander Hamilton, who has served as a private and wishes to have a commission in the regular army.
  - Philip Livingston, n.d.; Autograph
  - G. Montjoye de Froberg to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1800 January 30; ALS, 3 p.
    In French. Mentions General [Alexander] Hamilton, the exaggerations of Jacobin journalists, and a yellow fever quarantine.
  - G. Montjoye de Froberg to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1800 March 3; ALS, 3 p.
    In French. Mentions [Maria] Cosway and [Princess de] Craon. Contrary to what is in the papers, American [diplomats?] have been well received in England. Let General [Alexander] Hamilton know that.
  - John Lothrop Motley (1814-1877), n.d.; utograph,
  - Messrs. D'Orleans to Angelica Schuyler Church, Broadway, New York, New York., n.d.; LS, 1 p.
    Accepts an invitation.
  - Philip John Schuyler, Albany, New York, to [Angelica Schuyler Church]., 1782 September 20; ALS, 4 p.
    Mentions illnesses of Angelica and and his other daughter Margaret [Schuyler van Rensselaer]; refers to Chevalier De La Luzerne. Addressed to Mrs. Carter.
  - Philip John Schuyler, Albany, New York, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1788 May 28; ALS, 4 p.
    Comments on General Chatteleans' Journal. Discusses children: son Johnny [John Bradstreet] Schuyler's marriage to Miss [Elizabeth] van Rensselaer, his hopes to prosper, and their plans to live in the Schuyler house built in 1777; son Philip Schuyler as one who neglects his studies and is a disappointment; daughter Cornelia Schuyler as a historian; daughter Margaret Schuyler [van Rensselaer] as recovering from an illness. Mentions Monsieur De La Luzerne and Charles Talmadge and comments on Mr. [ ] Young as having great merit in his publications on his system in farming. Refers to the state convention to decide when the new Constitution will meet; says that the country must adopt, and states that "...when it is adopted this country will be a much more eligible residence than it is at present---"
  - Philip John Schuyler, Albany, New York, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1790 October 20; ALS, 2 p.